<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<articles>
    <article>
     
    <subject>Indian Geography</subject>
    <title>The Physical Divisions of India</title>
    <topic>Physical Geography</topic>
    <date>2026-05-24</date>
    <author>Tawqeer ul Islam</author>
    <summary>The first part of an in-depth series on India’s physiography, focusing on the origin, structural composition, and regional classification of the Great Himalayan Range.</summary>
    <content><![CDATA[
        <p>India’s physical landscape is a result of millions of years of geological processes, primarily the northward drift of the Indian Plate and its subsequent collision with the Eurasian Plate. This tectonic interaction created a land of extremes. To understand India's geography, we must categorize it into six distinct physiographic divisions. In this first installment, we explore the "Crown of India"—the Himalayas.</p>

        <div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
            <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e4/India_geography_map_en.svg/800px-India_geography_map_en.svg.png" alt="Physiographic Divisions of India" style="width:100%; max-width:650px; border:1px solid #ccc; border-radius:8px;"/>
            <p><small>Figure 1: The six major physical divisions of India. Source: Wikimedia Commons.</small></p>
        </div>

        <h3>The Himalayan Mountains: The Northern Sentinel</h3>
        <p>The Himalayas are geologically 'young' and structurally 'fold' mountains. They represent the loftiest and one of the most rugged mountain barriers in the world. They form an arc, which covers a distance of about 2,400 km. Their width varies from 400 km in Kashmir to 150 km in Arunachal Pradesh.</p>

        <h4>1. Geological Origin</h4>
        <p>According to the Theory of Plate Tectonics, the Himalayas were formed when the Indo-Australian plate collided with the Eurasian plate. The sedimentary rocks which were accumulated in the geosyncline known as the <strong>Tethys</strong> were folded to form the mountain system of western Asia and the Himalayas.</p>

        <div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
            <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c8/Himalayas_Formation.gif/400px-Himalayas_Formation.gif" alt="Formation of Himalayas" style="width:100%; max-width:400px; border-radius:8px;"/>
            <p><small>Figure 2: Animated representation of the Indian Plate's collision. Source: Wikimedia Commons.</small></p>
        </div>

        <h4>2. Longitudinal Divisions</h4>
        <p>The Himalayas consist of three parallel ranges in its longitudinal extent:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><strong>The Great or Inner Himalayas (Himadri):</strong> This is the most continuous range consisting of the loftiest peaks with an average height of 6,000 metres. It contains all prominent Himalayan peaks such as Mt. Everest, Kanchenjunga, and Nanga Parbat. The core of this part is composed of granite.</li>
            <li><strong>The Lesser Himalaya (Himachal):</strong> Lying to the south of the Himadri, this range is mainly composed of highly compressed and altered rocks. The altitude varies between 3,700 and 4,500 metres. Important ranges here include the Pir Panjal (the longest), the Dhauladhar, and the Mahabharat ranges.</li>
            <li><strong>The Shiwaliks:</strong> The outermost range of the Himalayas. They extend over a width of 10-50 km and have an altitude varying between 900 and 1100 metres. These ranges are composed of unconsolidated sediments. The longitudinal valleys lying between the Himachal and the Shiwaliks are known as <strong>Duns</strong> (e.g., Dehra Dun, Kotli Dun).</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>3. Regional Divisions (West to East)</h4>
        <p>Besides the longitudinal divisions, the Himalayas have been divided on the basis of regions from west to east, demarcated by river valleys:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><strong>Punjab Himalayas:</strong> Between the Indus and Satluj rivers.</li>
            <li><strong>Kumaon Himalayas:</strong> Between the Satluj and Kali rivers.</li>
            <li><strong>Nepal Himalayas:</strong> Between the Kali and Teesta rivers.</li>
            <li><strong>Assam Himalayas:</strong> Between the Teesta and Dihang (Brahmaputra) rivers.</li>
            <li><strong>Purvachal:</strong> Beyond the Dihang gorge, the Himalayas bend sharply to the south and spread along the eastern boundary of India, known as the Purvachal or Eastern hills (Patkai hills, Naga hills, Manipur hills, and Mizo hills).</li>
        </ul>

        <div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
            <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/00/Kanchenjunga_India.jpg/1024px-Kanchenjunga_India.jpg" alt="Mount Kanchenjunga" style="width:100%; max-width:650px; border-radius:8px;"/>
            <p><small>Figure 3: Kanchenjunga, the highest peak in India, located in the Himadri range. Source: Wikimedia Commons.</small></p>
        </div>

        <p>The Himalayas act as a climatic divide, preventing the cold Central Asian winds from entering the Indian subcontinent while trapping the Monsoon winds to provide rain. In the next section, we will descend from these heights to the fertile Northern Plains.</p>

        <!-- Continued from The Himalayas Section -->

        <h3>2. The Northern Plains: The Granary of India</h3>
        <p>The Northern Plains were formed by the alluvial deposits brought by three major river systems—the Indus, the Ganga, and the Brahmaputra—along with their tributaries. This plain is about 2,400 km long and 240 to 320 km broad. It is a geologically recent feature and is incredibly fertile, making it the agricultural heartland of India.</p>

        <div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
            <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/b3/Ganges_River_Plain.jpg/1024px-Ganges_River_Plain.jpg" alt="The Ganga Plains" style="width:100%; max-width:650px; border-radius:8px;"/>
            <p><small>Figure 4: The vast, fertile stretch of the Indo-Gangetic Plain. Source: Wikimedia Commons.</small></p>
        </div>

        <h4>Geomorphological Variations</h4>
        <p>The Northern Plains are not just flat lands; they exhibit significant relief features and are divided into four specific regions:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><strong>Bhabar:</strong> As rivers descend from the mountains, they deposit pebbles in a narrow belt (8-16 km wide) parallel to the Shiwaliks. In this region, most streams disappear underground.</li>
            <li><strong>Terai:</strong> South of the Bhabar, the streams re-emerge, creating a wet, swampy, and marshy region known as the Terai. Historically, this was a thickly forested region rich in wildlife.</li>
            <li><strong>Bhangar:</strong> This is the older alluvium of the plains, lying above the floodplains of the rivers. It presents a terrace-like feature. The soil here contains calcareous deposits locally known as <em>Kankar</em>.</li>
            <li><strong>Khadar:</strong> The newer, younger deposits of the floodplains. They are renewed almost every year by floods and are therefore highly fertile, ideal for intensive agriculture.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>Regional Divisions</h4>
        <p>The plain is broadly divided into three sections: The <strong>Punjab Plains</strong> (dominated by the Indus and its five tributaries), the <strong>Ganga Plains</strong> (extending between Ghaggar and Teesta rivers), and the <strong>Brahmaputra Plain</strong> (lying mainly in Assam).</p>

        <h3>3. The Peninsular Plateau: The Ancient Tableland</h3>
        <p>The Peninsular Plateau is a tableland composed of the old crystalline, igneous, and metamorphic rocks. It was formed by the breaking and drifting of the Gondwana land, making it one of the oldest and most stable landmasses on Earth. It is characterized by broad, shallow valleys and rounded hills.</p>

        <div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
            <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c2/Deccan_Plateau_Map.png/800px-Deccan_Plateau_Map.png" alt="Deccan Plateau Map" style="width:100%; max-width:500px; border:1px solid #ccc; border-radius:8px;"/>
            <p><small>Figure 5: Map illustrating the extent of the Deccan Plateau. Source: Wikimedia Commons.</small></p>
        </div>

        <h4>Major Sub-divisions</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><strong>The Central Highlands:</strong> Lying to the north of the Narmada river, this part covers a major area of the Malwa plateau. The Vindhyan range is bounded by the Central Highlands on the south and the Aravallis on the northwest. Further eastward extensions are known as Bundelkhand and Baghelkhand, ending at the mineral-rich Chota Nagpur plateau.</li>
            <li><strong>The Deccan Plateau:</strong> A triangular landmass south of the Narmada. It is higher in the west and slopes gently eastwards. An extension of the plateau is also visible in the northeast, locally known as the Meghalaya and Karbi-Anglong Plateau.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>The Western and Eastern Ghats</h4>
        <p>The edges of the Deccan Plateau are marked by the Western and Eastern Ghats:</p>
        <table style="width:100%; border-collapse: collapse; margin: 20px 0;">
            <tr style="background-color: #f2f2f2;">
                <th style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;">Feature</th>
                <th style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;">Western Ghats (Sahyadri)</th>
                <th style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;">Eastern Ghats</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;"><strong>Continuity</strong></td>
                <td style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;">Continuous; can be crossed through passes only.</td>
                <td style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;">Discontinuous and irregular; dissected by rivers.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;"><strong>Elevation</strong></td>
                <td style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;">Higher (900–1600 metres).</td>
                <td style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;">Lower (Average 600 metres).</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;"><strong>Highest Peak</strong></td>
                <td style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;">Anamudi (2,695 m).</td>
                <td style="border: 1px solid #ddd; padding: 8px;">Mahendragiri (1,501 m).</td>
            </tr>
        </table>

        <p>A distinct feature of the Peninsular plateau is the <strong>Deccan Trap</strong>—a black soil area of volcanic origin, which is exceptionally good for cotton cultivation.</p>

        <!-- To be continued with Desert, Coastal Plains, and Islands -->
        <!-- Continued from The Peninsular Plateau Section -->

        <h3>4. The Great Indian Desert (Thar Desert)</h3>
        <p>The Great Indian Desert, also known as the Thar Desert, lies towards the western margins of the Aravalli Hills. It is an undulating sandy plain covered with sand dunes. This region is a land of extreme temperatures and scarce vegetation, acting as a natural boundary between India and Pakistan.</p>

        <div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
            <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/52/Thar_Desert_Rajasthan.jpg/1024px-Thar_Desert_Rajasthan.jpg" alt="Sand Dunes in Thar Desert" style="width:100%; max-width:650px; border-radius:8px;"/>
            <p><small>Figure 6: The shifting sand dunes of the Thar Desert, Rajasthan. Source: Wikimedia Commons.</small></p>
        </div>

        <h4>Key Characteristics</h4>
        <ul>
            <li><strong>Climate:</strong> The region receives very low rainfall, below 150 mm per year, resulting in an arid climate with low vegetation cover.</li>
            <li><strong>Hydrology:</strong> Streams appear only during the rainy season. Shortly after, they disappear into the sand as they do not have enough water to reach the sea. The <strong>Luni</strong> is the only large river in this region.</li>
            <li><strong>Barchans:</strong> Crescent-shaped sand dunes called Barchans cover large areas, but longitudinal dunes become more prominent near the Indo-Pakistan border.</li>
        </ul>

        <h3>5. The Coastal Plains</h3>
        <p>The Peninsular plateau is flanked by a strip of narrow coastal plains, running along the Arabian Sea on the west and the Bay of Bengal on the east. These plains are vital for India's maritime trade, fishing, and agriculture.</p>

        <div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
            <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c5/Backwaters_of_Kerala.jpg/1024px-Backwaters_of_Kerala.jpg" alt="Kerala Backwaters" style="width:100%; max-width:650px; border-radius:8px;"/>
            <p><small>Figure 7: The Malabar Coast is famous for its extensive network of backwaters. Source: Wikimedia Commons.</small></p>
        </div>

        <h4>The Western Coastal Plain</h4>
        <p>Sandwiched between the Western Ghats and the Arabian Sea, it is a narrow plain consisting of three sections:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><strong>Konkan:</strong> The northern part (Mumbai – Goa).</li>
            <li><strong>Kannad Plain:</strong> The central stretch.</li>
            <li><strong>Malabar Coast:</strong> The southern stretch, famous for its lagoons and backwaters.</li>
        </ul>

        <h4>The Eastern Coastal Plain</h4>
        <p>The plains along the Bay of Bengal are wide and level. In the northern part, it is referred to as the <strong>Northern Circar</strong>, while the southern part is known as the <strong>Coromandel Coast</strong>. Large rivers such as the Mahanadi, Godavari, Krishna, and Kaveri have formed extensive deltas on this coast. Lake Chilika is an important feature along the eastern coast.</p>

        <h3>6. The Islands</h3>
        <p>India has two main groups of islands, which differ significantly in their geological origin and structure.</p>

        <div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
            <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/db/Havelock_Island%2C_Andaman.jpg/1024px-Havelock_Island%2C_Andaman.jpg" alt="Andaman Islands" style="width:100%; max-width:650px; border-radius:8px;"/>
            <p><small>Figure 8: Aerial view of the Andaman and Nicobar archipelago. Source: Wikimedia Commons.</small></p>
        </div>

        <h4>Lakshadweep Islands</h4>
        <p>Located in the Arabian Sea close to the Malabar coast of Kerala. This group of islands is composed of small <strong>coral islands</strong>. They cover a small area of 32 sq km. Kavaratti island is the administrative headquarters. This island group has great diversity of flora and fauna, including the Pitti Island, which is a bird sanctuary.</p>

        <h4>Andaman and Nicobar Islands</h4>
        <p>This is an elongated chain of islands located in the Bay of Bengal extending from north to south. They are bigger in size and are more numerous and scattered. These islands are believed to be an elevated portion of <strong>submarine mountains</strong>. They are of great strategic importance for the country and experience an equatorial climate with thick forest cover.</p>

        <h3>Conclusion: A Geographical Synthesis</h3>
        <p>A detailed survey of the physical divisions of India reveals that each region complements the others. The mountains are the major sources of water and forest wealth. The northern plains are the granaries of the country, providing the base for early civilizations. The plateau is a storehouse of minerals, which has played a crucial role in the industrialization of the country. Finally, the coastal regions and island groups provide sites for fishing and port activities. Thus, the diverse physical features of the land have immense future possibilities of development.</p>
    ]]></content>
    </article>




    <article>
        <subject>Accountancy</subject>
        <title>Understanding the Union Budget</title>
        <topic>Economics</topic>
        <date>2026-05-18</date>
        <author>CA Mohammad Lateef</author>
        <summary>A comprehensive breakdown of how the Union Budget is formulated and its impact on the economy.</summary>
        <content><![CDATA[
            <p>The Union Budget of India, also referred to as the Annual Financial Statement in Article 112 of the Constitution, is the annual budget of the Republic of India. The Government presents it on the first day of February so that it can be materialized before the beginning of the new financial year in April.</p>
            <h3>Core Components</h3>
            <p>The budget is divided into two major parts:</p>
            <ol>
                <li><strong>Revenue Budget:</strong> It includes the government's revenue receipts and expenditure.</li>
                <li><strong>Capital Budget:</strong> It includes capital receipts and payments, dealing with assets and liabilities.</li>
            </ol>
        ]]></content>
    </article>
</articles>